Finding Aid for Raymond Wesley Starr papers, 1860s-1968
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Raymond Wesley Starr papers 1860s-1968, 1936-1947
Starr, Raymond Wesley, 1888-1968.
1 folder
11 linear feet
8645 Aa 2; UAx
Grand Rapids, Michigan attorney, state attorney general, 1937-1938, associate justice and chief justice of the Michigan Supreme Court, U.S. District Court Judge for the Western District of Michigan. Correspondence, newspaper clippings, and business and professional papers, including material, 1950-1968, relating to his interest in Ferris State College, Big Rapids, Michigan; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Raymond W. Starr (donor no. 5096 )
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Raymond Starr was born August 24, 1888 in Pleasantview Township, Emmet County, Michigan. After graduating from Harbor Springs High School in 1906, he attended Ferris Institute (now Ferris State College) for one year, then entered the University of Michigan where he received his law degree in 1910. He then entered the law firm of Hyde, Earle & Thornton in Grand Rapids and in 1917, established the firm of Wicks, Fuller & Starr. In 1933, in association with his brother, James A. Starr, he founded the law firm of Starr and Starr.
In 1936 Starr was elected attorney general of Michigan. In 1941 he was appointed an associate justice of the Michigan Supreme Court and in 1945 served as chief justice of the court. In 1946 President Truman appointed Starr to be U.S. District Court Judge for the Western District of Michigan. He retired from full-time work on the court in 1961.
In addition to his judicial responsibilities, Starr also served as chairman of the Michigan Crime, Public Debt and Claims Commissions, as president of the D.A. Blodgett Homes for Children and the Michigan Children's Aid Society, as director of the Michigan Welfare League, and as member of the state Citizens' Advisory Committee known as the "Little Hoover" commission. He was chairman of the Board of Control at Ferris State College and member of the American Bar Associations, the American Law Institute, and the American Judicature Society. He died November 2, 1968.
The Starr collection consists primarily of correspondence from 1936 to 1947. These correspondence files are arranged alphabetically with the bulk of them dated 1946 to 1947, the period when Starr was first appointed U.S. District Court Judge for the Western District of Michigan. A smaller portion of the collection relates to Starr's association with Ferris State College, to his various other organization interests, and to his real estate and business activities.
Subjects:
Democratic Party (Mich.); Ferris State College.; Grand Rapids (Mich.); Judges--Michigan.; Lawyers--Michigan.; Michigan. Dept. of Attorney General.; Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan. Supreme Court.; Starr, Raymond Wesley, 1888-1968.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Lawyers--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Michigan. Dept. of Attorney General.; Starr, Raymond Wesley, 1888-1968.; Starr family.
Contributors:
Kent, W. Wallace (William Wallace), 1916-1973.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.
Genre Terms:
Ambrotypes.; Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - 1936 (A-Z), 6 folders (Box 1)
  - 1937-February 1939 (A-Z), 3 folders (Box 1)
  - March 1939-January 1940 (A-Z), 8 folders (Box 1)
  - February 1940-January 1941 (A-J), 3 folders (Box 1)
  - February 1940-January 1941 (K-Z), 5 folders (Box 2)
  - February 1941-1942 (A-Z), 4 folders (Box 2)
  - 1941-1943 (A-Q), 10 folders (Box 2)
  - 1941-1943 (R-Z), 4 folders (Box 3)
  - 1944-1945 (A-Z), 9 folders (Box 3)
  - 1946 (A-Z), 5 folders (Box 3)
  - 1945 (court correspondence) (Box 3)
  - 1946-1947
    - A (Box 4)
    - American Law Institute (Box 4)
    - Austin, Robert L. (Ionia State Hospital) (Box 4)
    - Ba-Bh (Box 4)
    - Bi-Bq (Box 4)
    - Br-Bz (Box 4)
    - Ca-Cg (Box 4)
    - Ch-Cq (Box 4)
    - Cr-Cz (Box 4)
    - Corpus Juris Secundum (Box 4)
    - Da-Dz (Box 4)
    - Democratic Party (Box 4)
    - Dolfin, John (Box 4)
    - E (Box 4)
    - Fa-Fk (Box 4)
    - Fl-Fz (Box 4)
    - Fox, Judge Noel (Box 4)
    - Ga-Gk (Box 4)
    - Gl-Gz (Box 4)
    - Gamble, Roy C. (Box 4)
    - General Services Administration (Box 4)
    - Grand Rapids Foundation (Box 4)
    - Grossman, Sidney (Box 4)
    - Ha-Hd (Box 5)
    - He-Hz (Box 5)
    - Hicks, Xen (Box 5)
    - Hoddinott, Henrietta (Box 5)
    - I-J (Box 5)
    - K (Box 5)
    - Kent, W. Wallace (Box 5)
    - La-Ln (Box 5)
    - Lo-Lz (Box 5)
    - Lederle, Arthur (Box 5)
    - Ma-Mb (Box 5)
    - Mc-Md (Box 5)
    - Me-Mn (Box 5)
    - Mo-Mz (Box 5)
    - Masonic (Box 5)
    - Michigan Gas and Electric Co. (Box 5)
    - Michigan State Board of Escheats (Box 5)
    - Michigan Welfare League (Box 5)
    - Moore, Mrs. Otto (Box 5)
    - N (Box 5)
    - National Labor Relations Board (Box 5)
    - O (Box 5)
    - O.P.A. (Box 5)
    - Pa-Ph (Box 6)
    - Pi-Pz (Box 6)
    - Pasic, Bartholomew (Box 6)
    - Postmaster (Box 6)
    - Q (Box 6)
    - Ra-Rh (Box 6)
    - Ri-Rz (Box 6)
    - Robes-Judicial (Box 6)
    - Rowley, Ella Jane (Box 6)
    - Sa-Sd (Box 6)
    - Se-Sk (Box 6)
    - Sl-Sq (Box 6)
    - St-Sz (Box 6)
    - Shaine (H.B.) & Co. (Box 6)
    - Starr, James A. (Box 6)
    - Starr, Raymond (Biographical) (Box 6)
    - Starr, Mrs. Raymond (Box 6)
    - State Bar of Michigan (Box 6)
    - T-V, 5 folders (Box 6)
    - United Smelters (Box 6)
    - Van Etten, William (Box 6)
    - Wa-Wn (Box 6)
    - Wo-Wz (Box 6)
    - West Publishing Co. (Box 6)
    - White, W. Page (Box 6)
    - Williams, G. Mennen (Box 6)
    - X-Y-Z (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous papers
  - Ferris Institute (Box 7)
  - Ferris Institute (Box 8)
    (continued)
  - Fact finding Board 1941-1946 (Box 9)
  - State Supreme Court election 1945 (Box 9)
  - Grand Rapids Historical Society 1951-1952 (Box 9)
  - James Foster Foundation 1951-1953 (Box 9)
  - Mayo Clinic 1948 (Box 9)
  - Appointment as U.S. District Judge 1945-1949 (Box 9)
  - Michigan Federation of Labor essay contest 1952 (Box 9)
  - Catholic Service Bureau Workshop on the Problems of Juveniles (Box 9)
  - American Bar Association Committee on Traffic Court Programs 1954-1956 (Box 9)
  - Michigan Highway Safety Seminar 1952-1953 (Box 9)
  - Additional judge for district, and increase in salary of federal judges 1949-1953 (Box 9)
  - Speech: "The History of the Development of the Law" 1959 (Box 9)
  - Michigan Air Academy Committee 1953 (Box 9)
  - Newspaper clippings 1921-1961 (Box 9)
  - Photographs, 2 envelopes (Box 9)
    (see also earlier family ambrotypes stored in Spec. Loc. UAx)
  - Real estate and business papers (Box 10)
  - Real estate and business papers (Box 11)